Carlos G. Poses

Utrecht, Netherlands

 \square +34 622 01 23 51 • \square carlosgonzalezposes@gmail.com \square 0000-0002-6546-838X

About

I am a Statistics MSc student with a passion in scientific research. My goal is to make the scientific literature more solid and trustful via the use of statistics. I have a background in (empirical) social science and three years of research experience in survey methodology. I am a strong believer in the importance of methodological rigor, open science and transparency.

Professional experience

Researcher at Universitat Pompeu Fabra

2020-2022

Research and Expertise Centre for Survey Methodology (RECSM)

Barcelona

- Main responsibility: Analysis of cross-cultural comparability (measurement invariance) and measurement quality (MTMM experiments) of European Social Survey data
- \odot Finished job as team leader of ESS work programme, entailing structured training and supervision of new RECSM members
- Writing of scientific reports and papers
- Involvement in ESS pilot experiments and questionnaire design, consulting, data analysis, literature reviews

Junior researcher at Universitat Pompeu Fabra

2019-2020

Research and Expertise Centre for Survey Methodology (RECSM)

Barcelona

- $\odot\,$ Member of the Advanced Survey Quality Methods research group
- O Data analysis, internal management group tasks, literature reviews, scientific reports

Education

MSc Methodology and Statistics

2022 - 2024

Utrecht University

Utrecht, Netherlands

- O Focus: Applied statistics in the Behavioural, Biomedical and Social Sciences
- Electives: Applied Data Science track and Introduction to Complex Systems (both starting 09/2023)

BA Philosophy, Politics and Economics

2016 - 2020

UPF, UC3M and UAM

Barcelona/Madrid

- \odot Interuniveristary degree among 3 top Spanish universities in the Social Sciences. 5/8 semesters at UPF; 2/8 semesters at UC3M/UAM. Average grade: 8.8/10
- O Specialization: Statistics and Research Methodology, Empirical social science
- O Received La Caixa mobility scholarship to study 2nd year in Madrid
- \odot Thesis: Content Validity and Measurement Quality of the "Satisfaction With Democracy" Survey Indicator. Grade: 10/10. Became a published paper

Erasmus+ student 2019–2020

KU Leuven Leuven, Belgium

One semester. Faculty of Economics and Business

Peer-reviewed publications

- 1. Poses, C., & Revilla, M. (2021). Measuring satisfaction with democracy: How good are different scales across countries and languages? *European Political Science Review*, 1–18. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1755773921000266
- 2. Poses, C., Revilla, M., Schwarz, H., Asensio, M., & Weber, W. (2021). Measurement quality of 67 common social sciences questions across countries and languages based on 28 Multitrait-Multimethod experiments implemented in the European Social Survey. Survey Research Methods., 15(3), 235–256. https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.18148/srm/2021.v15i3.7816
- 3. Revilla, M., Poses, C., Serra, O., Asensio, M., Schwarz, H., & Weber, W. (2021). Applying the Estimation Using Pooled Data Approach to the Multitrait-Multimethod Experiments of the European Social Survey (Rounds 1 to 7). Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal, 28(3), 463–474. https://doi.org/10.1080/10705511.2020.1807988

Professional reports

- 1. Weber, W., Poses, C., & Jaime, S. (2022). Three-group SB-MTMM experiment with measures of the Sexism scale from the Rotating Module "Gender in Contemporary Europe: Rethinking Equality and the Backlash." *European Social Survey*.
- 2. Poses, C., & Weber, W. (2022). Pretest of ESS Round 11 rotating modules in Lithuania and United Kingdom: Analysis of completion time. *European Social Survey*.
- 3. Poses, C., Weber, W., & Nickel, A. (2022). Measurement invariance and quality of the attitudes towards immigration scale across ESS Rounds 1-9 (2002-2018). *European Social Survey*.
- 4. Poses, C., & Weber, W. (2021). Evaluation of measurement quality and cross-country comparison of complex concepts [Positive and Negative Affect]. European Social Survey.
- 5. Poses, C., Weber, W., & Schwarz, H. (2020). Estimating measurement quality in Round 9 of the European Social Survey Results of a Split-Ballot Multitrait Multimethod experiment. *European Social Survey*.

Research Projects

European Social Survey (ESS) ERIC - Core Scientific Team (CST): PI - Dr. Wiebke Weber. Project date: 2008-Ongoing. Participation since 2019 until 2022

Survey Quality Predictor: PI - Dr. Wiebke Weber. Project date: 2008-2022 Participation since 2019.

Academic presentations/conferences

- Poses, C., Revilla, M., Asensio, M., Schwarz, H., and Weber, W (2021). An overview of the size of measurement errors of a subset of questions of the European Social Survey. European Survey Research Association 2021 Conference
- Poses, C., Schwarz, H., and Weber, W. (2021). Estimating measurement quality in Round 9 of the European Social Survey Results of a Split-Ballot Multitrait Multimethod experiment. *European Survey Research Association 2021 Conference*
- Poses, C, and Revilla, M. (2020). Estimating the size of measurement errors of the "Satisfaction With Democracy" Survey Indicator for different scales, countries and languages. "RECSM Seminar Series
- O Assistant to: ESRA Conference 2021, BigSurv 2020, RECSM Seminar Series

Additional training

- O RECSM Summer School 2021: Structural Equation Modelling (8h)
- O RECSM Summer School 2020: Survey experiments (8h), Causal inference with non-experimental data (12h), Sampling Methods (8h), Introduction to R (8h)
- O RECSM Summer School 2019: Practical multilevel modeling (12h)

Consultancy projects

CIDOB (Barcelona)

2020-2021

Assistance to Barcelona Centre for International Affairs

- Online elite survey within the project: "CAScading Climate risks: towards ADaptive and resilient European Societies (CASCADES)"
- O Role: Data wrangling, descriptive data analysis and visualization using R (tidyverse based)

Centre d'Estudis d'Opinió

2023

Survey data quality consulting for Catalan government Public Opinion Institute

 Analysis of data quality of the first wave of a new online barometer about sociopolitical attitudes (with Melanie Revilla and Carlos Ochoa). Role: questionnaire review, first wave data quality analysis (completion times, straightlining, mode effects, non-response, experimental analysis, and more), data wrangling, data analysis and visualization, writing of report and recommedations

Sofware

- Proficient: R, including RMarkdown, Microsoft Office (PowerPoint, Word, Excel)
- o Intermediate: Lisrel, Git/Github
- O Basic: Stata (basic), SPSS (basic)

Languages

- English (Fluent TOEFL 115/120, equivalent to C2), Galician (Native), Spanish (Native),
 Catalan (Fluent, C1 accredited), Portuguese (reading).
- O Willingness to learn Dutch

April, 2023. This CV has been compiled using RMarkdown and the R package vitae.